Bibliography of Jamestown Sources
National Park Service, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, College of William and Mary
- Other Monographs
  - ---. The Virginia Adventure, Roanoke to James Towne: An Archaeological and Historical Odyssey. 1994., 319; Xxviii, 491 pp.; illus., maps.
    Interweaves contemporary accounts with descriptions of excavations and artifacts to reveal the motivations of the first adventurers to Roanoke and Jamestown and tell the story of how the English presence persisted in spite of bad luck, bad management, and bad relations with IndiansBibliography: 459-67. Includes index.
  - Norfolk and Western Railway Company. A Hand-book: Historic Virginia, Ye Birthplace of Ye Nation; Issued by Ye Norfolk & Western Railway, Ye Route to Ye Jamestown Exposition. [1906]., 320; [16] pp.; illus., maps (some col.)
  - Nugent, Nell Marion. Cavaliers and Pioneers: Abstracts of Virginia Land Patents and Grants. 1934., 321; Xxxv, 767 pp.; illus., maps, chart.
    Contains abstracts of records in Virginia Land Office patent books 1 through 5. Mrs. Nugent, custodian of the Land Office from 1925 to 1958, had planned a series of five volumes covering the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. Records in patent books 6 through 14 were abstracted, but they were not published until the Virginia State Library issued volumes 2 and 3 in 1977 and 1979 respectively.The introduction to volume 1 includes a list of those Ancient Planters known to have come to Virginia by the end of 1616, survived the 1622 massacre, and appeared in the 1624/5 muster as then living in Virginia.Several reprints: Baltimore, Genealogical Publishing Co., 1963-1991.
  - ---. Cavaliers and Pioneers: Abstracts of Virginia Land Patents and Grants. 1977-1979., 322
    Volume 2 contains abstracts of records in patent books 6, 7, and 8; volume 3 covers patent books 9 through 14
    In 1994 the Virginia Genealogical Society published volume 4: 1732-1741 (patent books 15 through 19) and volume 5: 1741-1749 (patent books 20 through 28). The Society plans to publish volumes 6 and 7 covering patent books 29 through 42 (1749-1774).
  - The Official Blue Book of the Jamestown Ter-centennial Exposition, A.D. 1907: The Only Authorized History of the Celebration. Norfolk: Colonial Publishing Co. 1909., 323; Viii, 806 pp.; photos.
    Comprehensive coverage of exhibits, events, awards, and statisticsIncludes indexes.
  - Old Dominion Pilgrimage Committee. Pilgrimage to Jamestown Island and Colonial Homes of Virginia., 324; [32] pp.; illus.
  - Old Dominion Society of the City of New York. First Celebration of the Anniversary of the Settlement at Jamestown, Va., on the 13th of May, 1607. 1860., 325; 109 pp.
    George W. Summers, orator.
  - Oldmixon, John. The British Empire in America, Containing the History of the Discovery, Settlement, Progress and Present State of All the British Colonies on the Continent and Islands of America. 1708., 326; 2 vols.; maps (by Herman Moll).
    Second edition: London, 1741, 2 vols.; reprint: New York, A. M. Kelley, 1969.
  - Order of First Families of Virginia, 1607-1620. Celebration Commemorating the Fiftieth Anniversary, Order of First Families of Virginia, 1607-1620, Jamestown, Virginia, May 12-13, 1962., 327; [16] pp.
  - Order of United Commercial Travelers of America. Old Dominion Council, No. 298 (Norfolk, Va.) Souvenir Celebrating the Eleventh Annual Session, Grand Council, Kentucky, Virginias, Maryland and District of Columbia, U. C. T. of America, Commemorating Jamestown Exposition., 328; 96 pp.; illus.
  - Our Lady of Czestochowa Parish (Worcester, Mass.) First Poles in America, in Commemoration of the 350th Anniversary of Their Landing at Jamestown, Virginia, October 1, 1608. 1958., 329; 32 pp.; illus., portraits., facsim., map.
  - Page, Rosewell. First Permanent English Settlements in America. [192-?], 330; 8 pp.
    "Compliments of Colonial Dames of America in the state of Virginia."
  - Page, Thomas Nelson. The Old Dominion: Her Making and Her Manners. 1909., 331; Viii, 407 pp.; plates, col. illus.
    Contents include: The beginning of America; Jamestown, the birthplace of the American people; Colonial life.
  - Paine, Lauran. Captain John Smith and the Jamestown Story. [1973]., 332; 206 pp.; illus.
    Bibliography: 200-201.
  - Pender, George L. The Early Settlement of Jamestown., 333
  - Pennsylvania. Jamestown Exposition Commission. Pennsylvania at the Jamestown Exposition, Hampton Roads, Va., 1907. 1908., 334; 360 pp.; illus., portraits, folded plan.
    Prepared by James H. Lambert, executive officer.
  - Pennsylvania Railroad. The Participation by the Pennsylvania Railroad System in the Jamestown Ter-centennial Exposition, Norfolk, Virginia, April 26th-November 30th, 1907., 335; [16] pp.; illus.
  - Percy, George. Observations Gathered out of "A Discourse on the Plantation of the Southern Colony in Virginia by the English, 1606." [1967]., 336; Xv, 27 pp.
    First published in 1625 in vol. 4 of Purchas His Pilgrimes, compiled by Samuel Purchas. Apparently based on the author's lost journal for the period December 1606 to September 1607, called by Purchas A Discourse of the Plantation of the Southern Colony of Virginia by the English, 1606.
  - Perry, William Stevens, ed. Papers Relating to the History of the Church in Virginia, A.D.1650-1776. 1870., 337; Xvii, 585 pp.
    Includes brief accounts of the fortifications at Jamestown in the 1690s and indications of ministers there in the early eighteenth centuryIncludes bibliographical references, and an index
    Reprint: New York, AMS Press, 1969, as vol. 1 of Historical Collections Relating to the American Colonial Church.
  - Peterson, Harold L. Arms and Armor in Colonial America, 1526-1783. 1956., 338; 350 pp.; illus.
    The first section of the volume has separate chapters on firearms, ammunition and equipment, edged weapons, and armor during the age of colonization and exploration, 1526-1688. Included are references to equipment sent to Jamestown and items uncovered in recent excavationsBibliography: 337-45. Includes index.
  - Pocahontas Coal Operators Association. Pocahontas Coal Operators Association Exhibit at the Jamestown Exposition, Norfolk, Va., 1907., 339; 24 pp.
  - Posey, Jon Millar. The Descendants of John Thomas Who Came to Jamestown, Virginia, in the Year 1622: This Family Settled in Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina and Georgia. [197-?], 340; 25 leaves.
  - Powell, William Stevens. John Pory, 1572-1636: The Life and Letters of a Man of Many Parts. 1977., 341; Xviii, 187 pp.
    6 microfiches; plates, illusPory was in Virginia from 1619 to 1622, serving as Secretary of the Colony and Speaker of the first General Assembly, and again in 1624, as a member of a royal commission of inquiryIncludes bibliographic references, and indexes of the book and the microfiche supplementMicrofiche supplement (6 sheets, 393 pp.): "Letters and Other Minor Writings."The contents of the supplement are listed in the Appendix of the book.
  - Protestant Episcopal Church in the U.S.A. Committee on the Robert Hunt Memorial Fund. Robert Hunt Memorial., 342; [14] pp.; plates.
    An appeal for funds for the Robert Hunt Memorial, to be erected at Jamestown, 1907. Issued under the authority of the committee of the Protestant Episcopal Church, dioceses of Virginia and West Virginia. Preface signed: William W. Old, treasurer.
  - Pryor, Sara Agnes Rice. The Birth of the Nation: Jamestown, 1607. 1907., 343; Xvi, 352 pp.; front., plates, portraits.
    Illustrations by William de Leftwich DodgeAlso published in 1911 by Grosset and Dunlap.
  - Pulaski County (Va.) Commission, Jamestown Exposition, 1907. Pulaski County, Virginia: A Historic and Descriptive Sketch Designed to Show Forth the Natural Advantages, Resources and General Adaptability of the Banner County of Southwest Virginia, to Agriculture, Cattle Raising, and Also Commercial and Industrial Enterprises., 344
    Published under the direction of the Committee in charge of the Pulaski County exhibit at the Jamestown Exposition of 1907.
  - Pullen, William Edward. A Virginia Genealogy: From Jamestown, Yorktown and Appomattox, to the Argonne, the Beaches of Normandy and Iwo Jima, in the Annals of the Hilldrups, Guerrants and Their Allied Virginia Families. 1978., 345; 178 pp.
  - Purchas, Samuel, comp. Hakluytus Posthumus, or Purchas His Pilgrimes, Contayning a History of the World, in Sea Voyages, and Lande Travells, by Englishmen and Others. 1625., 346; 4 vols.; illus., maps.
    Some left written by Mr. Hakluyt at his death. More since added, his also perused, and perfected. All examined, abreviated, illustrated with notes. Enlarged with discourses, adorned with pictures, and expressed in mapps. In fower parts. Each containing five bookes. [Title page]Reprint: Hakluyt Society Publications, extra ser., vols. 14-33; Glasgow, 1905-1907.
  - ---. Purchas His Pilgrimage, or Relations of the World and the Religions Observed in Al Ages and Places Discovered, from the Creation unto This Present. In Foure Parts: This First Contayneth a Theologicall and Geographicall Historie of Asia, Africa, and America, with the Ilands Adiacent... With Briefe Descriptions of the Countries, Nations, States, Discoveries, Private and Publike Customes, and the Most Remarkable Rarities of Nature, or Humane Industrie, in the Same. 1617., 347; 1102 pp.
    Material on Virginia appears in chapters V and VI of The Eighth Booke: America, pages 937-57, as follows:Chap. V: Of Virginia I. The Preface, Sir Walter Raleighs Plantation, and the Northerne ColonieII. Of the Southerne Plantation and Colonies, and Many Causes Alledged of the Ill Success Thereof at the First III. Of the Soile, People, Beasts, Commodities and Other Observations of Virginia IIII. Of the Present Estate of Virginia, and the English There ResidingChap. VI: Of the Religion and Rites of the Virginians [Indians] I. Of the Virginian Rites, Related by Master HariotII. Observations of Their Rites by Captaine Smith and Others III. Of the Sasquesahanockes, with Other, and Later Observations of the Virginian RitesAn index is appendedEarlier editions: 1613 and 1614
    The fourth edition (1626) is generally found as volume 1 or volume 5 of the author's Hakluytus Posthumus.
  - Quinn, David B. England and the Discovery of America, 1481-1620, from the Bristol Voyages of the Fifteenth Century to the Pilgrim Settlement at Plymouth: The Exploration, Exploitation, and Trial-and-Error Colonization of North America by the English. 1974., 348; Xxiv, [516] pp.; maps, plates.
    A brief final chapter discusses the motives of the English investors in the Virginia Company Bibliography: 493-97. Includes index.
  - Rand McNally and Company. Description of the Jamestown Exposition, Celebrating the First Permanent English Settlement in America, Combined with a Complete Atlas of the World. [1907]., 349; 244 pp.; illus., col. maps.
  - Randolph, Edmund. History of Virginia. 1970., 350; Xliv, 347 pp.
    Randolph began collecting materials for his History in the 1780s, while he was governor, and had almost finished writing it when he died in 1813. The manuscript had been known and available to scholars at the Virginia Historical Society for many years before it was printed in 1970
    Much of the early part of the work consists of passages taken more or less verbatim from William Stith's history of Virginia... The editor has also added those portions of John Marshall's Life of Washington and David Hume's History of England that Randolph clearly intended to includeIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Rasmussen, William M. S., and Robert Steven Tilton. Pocahontas: Her Life and Legend. 1994., 351; 56 pp.; illus.
    Published for an exhibition at the Virginia Historical Society, October 1994 through April 1995
    Includes bibliographical references: 52-56.
  - Reasons Why the Government Should Acquire a Portion of the Jamestown Exposition Grounds and Establish There a Naval Training Station. [19--]., 352; 8 pp.
  - Reinhart, Theodore R., and Dennis J. Pogue, eds. The Archaeology of Seventeenth-Century Virginia. 1993., 353; Ix, 402 pp.; illus.
    Papers originally presented at the 5th Symposium on Virginia Archaeology, sponsored by the Council of Virginia Archaeologists, Williamsburg, May 10-11, 1991
    Contents include: Seventeenth-century Virginia and its twentieth-century archaeologists, by Carter L. Hudgins; Private fortifications in seventeenth-century Virginia: A study of six representative works, by Charles T. Hodges; A scant urbanity: Jamestown in the seventeenth century, by Kathleen Bragdon, Edward Chappell, and William GrahamIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Report of the Proceedings of the Late Jubilee at James-town in Commemoration of the 13th May, the Second Centesimal Anniversary of the Settlement of Virginia; Containing the Order of Procession, the Prayer of Bishop Madison, the Orations, the Odes and Toasts; Together with the Proceedings at Williamsburg on the 15th, the Day When the Convention of Virginia Assembled in the Old Capitol, Declared Her Independent and Recommended a Similar Procedure to Congress and to the Other States. 1807., 354; 48 pp.
  - Reps, John William. 1972., 355; Xii, 345 pp.
    illus., mapsArgues that town planning played an important role in colonization and discusses the forms and designs used in planning colonial towns. Included is coverage of efforts to encourage the development of Jamestown and other Virginia townsBibliography: 321-28. Includes index.
  - Richmond-Jamestown Festival Committee. Report, December 31, 1957., 356; [44] leaves.
  - Richmond Times-Dispatch. Jamestown, 1607-1957: The Jamestown Festival, April 1 through November 30, 357; 84 pp.
    illus., map.
  - Riggs, David F. Embattled Shrine: Jamestown in the Civil War. 1997., 358; Xii, 212 pp.; illus., maps.
    Bibliography: 178-96. Includes index.
  - Riley, Edward M., and Charles E. Hatch, Jr., eds. James Towne in the Words of Contemporaries. 1955., 359; Iv, 36 pp.; illus., portraits.
    "...a presentation of excerpts and selections from records, laws, accounts, and descriptions made by men who lived in, or were associated with, 'James Towne'". [Introduction]Bibliography: 35-36
    Previous edition: Washington, National Park Service, 1944.
  - Robertson, Wyndham. Pocahontas, Alias Matoaka, and Her Descendants through Her Marriage at Jamestown, Virginia, in April, 1614, with John Rolfe, Gentleman; Including the Names of Alfriend, Archer, Bentley, Bernard, Bland, Bolling, Branch, Cabell, Catlett, Cary, Dandridge, Dixon, Douglas, Duval, Eldridge, Ellett, Ferguson, Field, Fleming, Gay, Gordon, Griffin, Grayson, Harrison, Hubard, Lewis, Logan, Markham, Meade, McRae, Murray, Page, Poythress, Randolph, Robertson, Skipwith, Stanard, Tazewell, Walke, West, Whittle, and Others. 1887., 360; Vii, 84 pp.; front., plates.
    ...with Biographical Sketches by Wyndham Robertson, and Illustrative Historical Notes by R. A. BrockIndex published separately: Burns, Pocahontas Blood, Being an Index..., 1983 (ENTRY 126).Various reprints, including Baltimore, Genealogical Publishing Co., 1993
    For corrections and additions, see Brown and Myers, Pocahontas' Descendants: A Revision... (ENTRY 113).
  - Robinson, Sam. The Mother-in-Law Tree., 361; [5] pp.; illus.
    Sam Robinson was the Sexton at the Jamestown church.
  - Robinson, Walter Stitt. Mother Earth: Land Grants in Virginia, 1607-1699. 1957., 362; 77 pp.; plates.
    Bibliography: 75-77
    Reprints: Charlottesville, University Press of Virginia, 1980; Baltimore, For Clearfield Co. by Genealogical Publishing Co., 1993.
  - Rolfe, John. A True Relation of the State of Virginia Lefte by Sir Thomas Dale, Knight, in May Last 1616. [1971]., 363; Xliv, 15 pp.
    Earlier printings: 1) Southern Literary Messenger 5 (1839): 401-6; 2) Virginia Historical Register 1 (1848): 101-13; 3) Edited by J. C. Wylie, F. L. Berkeley, Jr., and John M. Jennings, New Haven, 1951.
  - Rosbotham, Lyle. Jamestown Island: Photographs. 1976., 364; [55] pp.; chiefly col. illus.
  - Rountree, Helen C. Pocahontas's People: The Powhatan Indians of Virginia through Four Centuries. 1990., 1204; Xii, 404 pp.; illus., maps.
    Bibliography: 363-87. Includes index.
  - ---. The Powhatan Indians of Virginia: Their Traditional Culture. 1989., 365; Viii, 221 pp.; illus., maps.
    A description of the Indian culture encountered by the Jamestown colonists, based mainly on archaeology and such early accounts as those of John Smith, William Strachey, Henry Spelman, George Percy, and Gabriel ArcherBibliography: 194-206. Includes index.
  - Rowsey, Robert N.,. The Glorious March to the Sea: A Story of the Record-breaking March of One Hundred and Thirty-Four Miles in Five Days by the Richmond Howitzers to the Jamestown Exposition, June, 1907. [1907?], 366; 106 pp.; illus.
  - Rutherford, Mildred Lewis. Facts and Figures vs. Myths and Misrepresentations: The True History of the Jamestown Colony. [192-]., 367; 24 pp.
    Bibliography: [2].
  - Ryan, Thomas Fortune. The London Company of Virginia: A Brief Account of Its Transactions in Colonizing Virginia, with Photogravures of the More Prominent Leaders Reproduced from the Collection of Historical Portraits at Oakridge, Nelson County, Virginia, Secured for Exhibition at the Jamestown Exposition. 1908., 368; 21, [46] pp.; portraits.
    Introduction signed by James Taylor Ellyson.
  - Sams, Conway Whittle. The Conquest of Virginia: The Forest Primeval; An Account, Based on Original Documents, of the Indians in That Portion of the Continent in Which Was Established the First English Colony in America. 1916., 369; Xxiii, 432 pp.; illus., maps.
  - ---. The Conquest of Virginia: The Second Attempt; An Account, Based on Original Documents, of the Attempt, under the King's Form of Government, to Found Virginia at Jamestown, 1606-1610. 1929., 370; Xlix, 916 pp.; illus., plates, portraits, maps, plans.
    Includes bibliographical referencesReprint: Spartanburg, S.C., Reprint Co., 1973.
  - ---. The Conquest of Virginia: The Third Attempt, 1610-1624. 1939., 371; 824 pp.
  - Scheeps-togt van Anthony Chester na Virginia, gedaan in het jaar 1620, beschreeven door een voornaam reysiger, die dese togt mede gedaan heest. (Voyage of Anthony Chester to Virginia, Made in the Year 1620, Narrated by a Distinguished Passenger, Who Participated in This Expedition). 1707., 372; 15 pp.; folded plates.
    Translation in William and Mary Quarterly 9 (1901): 203-14.
  - Shea, William L. The Virginia Militia in the Seventeenth Century. 1983., 373; Xi, 152 pp.; 2 maps.
    A study of the militia's role in the military defense and internal affairs of Virginia in the seventeenth century, including confrontations with the Indians, two raids by the Dutch navy, and Bacon's RebellionBibliography: 141-48. Includes index.
  - Shiner, Joel Lewis. Report on Archeological Excavations in the Area of the State House Group in the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities Ground (Jamestown National Historic Site) at Jamestown. 1955., 374; 9 pp.; maps, plates.
    Typescript.
  - Short, Jo Stallings. A Stallings Family History from Jamestown, Virginia, to Albemarle, North Carolina. 1984., 375; Xi, 89 pp.; illus., maps.
    Bibliography: 84-86. Includes index.
  - Simpson, Edith Jenkins. The Stegall Family of Pontotoc County, Mississippi, from 1735, Jamestown, Virginia, to 1991, Pontotoc County, Mississippi. 1991., 376; 662 pp.; illus.
    Includes index
    Supplement, by Charline Roye Henderson and Edith Jenkins Simpson; Tupelo, Miss., 1992; 160 pp., illus., includes index.
  - Simpson, William S. Biographical Data on the Original 104 Settlers Who Landed at Jamestown, Virginia, in May 1607. 1968., 377; 13 leaves.
    Photocopy of typescriptBibliography: 13.
  - Smith, Gloria L. Colonial Interiors: Lesser-known Histories of Early Virginia Colonies of Jamestown, Middle Plantation, Williamsburg, and Martin's Hundred (Carter's Grove Plantation); Cultural and Technical Diversity at Work. 1992., 378; 66 leaves; illus.
    Includes bibliographical referencesOriginal edition: 1990.
  - Smith, James Morton, ed. Seventeenth-Century America: Essays in Colonial History. 1959., 379; Xv, 238 pp.
    Essays based on papers read at the Symposium on Seventeenth-Century Colonial History, a commemorative event sponsored by the Institute of Early American History and Culture to celebrate the 350th anniversary of the Jamestown settlement, Williamsburg, April 7-12, 1957
    Contents include: The moral and legal justifications for dispossessing the Indians, by Wilcomb E. Washburn; Indian cultural adjustment to European civilization, by Nancy Oestreich Lurie; Social origins of some early Americans, by Mildred Campbell; Politics and social structure in Virginia, by Bernard Bailyn; Seventeenth-century English historians of America, by Richard S. Dunn.Includes bibliographical references, and an index.
  - Smith, John. Capt. John Smith of Willoughby by Alford, Lincolnshire, President of Virginia and Admiral of New England: Works, 1608-1631. 1884., 380; Cxxxvi, 984 pp.; maps, facsim.
    Smith's works which deal with Virginia include1) A True Relation of Such Occurrences and Accidents of Noate as Hath Hapned in Virginia since the First Planting of That Collony (1608);2) A Map of Virginia, with a Description of the Countrey (1612), with its second part,3) The Proceedings of the English Colonie in Virginia since Their First Beginning from England in the Yeare of Our Lord 1606, till This Present 1612;4) The Generall Historie of Virginia, New-England, and the Summer Isles..., Divided into Sixe Bookes (1624), Books 2 and 3 of which are reprints, with variations, of A Map of Virginia and The Proceedings of the English Colony in Virginia, and Book 4 is a continuation of the history of Virginia from the time Smith left it until 1624;5) The True Travels, Adventures, and Observations of Captaine John Smith (1630), which is predominantly about the early years of Smith's life before his Virginia voyage, but which includes a short account of Virginia events from 1624 to 1629
    Edward Arber's introduction to this compilation of Smith's works includes the texts of several "Illustrative Documents," such asa) "A Relatyon of the Discovery of Our River, from James Forte into the Maine..., Sincerely Writen and Observed by a Gent. of Ye Colony" [possibly Gabriel Archer], covering the period from May 21 to June 22, 1607;b) "Observations Gathered out of 'A Discourse of the Plantation of the Southerne Colonie in Virginia by the English, 1606', Written by That Honorable Gentleman, Master George Percy," taken from Samuel Purchas's Pilgrimes;c) "A Discourse of Virginia," by Edward Maria Wingfield (1608);d) "Relation of Virginea," by Henry Spelman (1613)Later edition: Travels and Works of Captain John Smith, Edinburgh, 1910, 2 vols., with a new introduction by A. G. Bradley.
  - ---. Captain John Smith: A Select Edition of His Writings. 1988., 381; 290 pp.
  - ---. The Complete Works of Captain John Smith (1580-1631) in Three Volumes. 1986., 382; 1986. 3 vols.; illus., maps.
    A complete and annotated edition of all Smith's works, including some omitted by Arber. Includes a biographical directory of Elizabethan and Jacobean persons with some connection to Smith, a brief biography of Smith, a facsimile of the original printing of the True Relation, and an index
    Bibliography (prepared by David B. Quinn): vol. 3, 393-433.